<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The seale of the churches safetie; or A sermon preached at Norwich, the fift of Nouember, 1616 Wherein is opened the sealed assurance of the safetie of the Church, in all times, and estates, meete for all Christians to know, and acknowledge, to the glorie of God, and their owne comfort in life and death. By N. Colt, one of the preachers appointed by publike authoritie for the common-place there.</title>
            <title>Seale of the churches safetie.</title>
            <author>Colt, Nicholas, d. 1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19174</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118542</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19144</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19174)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19144)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 577:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The seale of the churches safetie; or A sermon preached at Norwich, the fift of Nouember, 1616 Wherein is opened the sealed assurance of the safetie of the Church, in all times, and estates, meete for all Christians to know, and acknowledge, to the glorie of God, and their owne comfort in life and death. By N. Colt, one of the preachers appointed by publike authoritie for the common-place there.</title>
                  <title>Seale of the churches safetie.</title>
                  <author>Colt, Nicholas, d. 1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 73, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A1 is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19144:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19144:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19144:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19144:2"/>
            <p>The Seale of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſafetie; OR <hi>A Sermon preached at</hi> NORWICH, the fift of Nouember, 1616.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is opened the ſealed aſſurance of</hi> the ſafetie of the CHVRCH, in all times, <hi>and eſtates, meete for all Chriſtians to know, and acknowledge, to the</hi> glorie of God, and their owne comfort in life and death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> N. COLT, <hi>one of the Preachers appointed by publike authoritie for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-place there.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. TIM. 2.19.</bibl>
               <p>The foundation of God remayneth ſure, and hath this Seale, The Lord knoweth, &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>PSAL. 3.8.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saluation belongeth to the Lord, and his bleſſing is vpon his People.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>W. Stansby.</hi> 1617.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19144:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19144:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL AND RELIGIOVS Magiſtrates, Chriſtian So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, and other Inhabitants of the Citie of NORWICH, <hi>ſauing-health in</hi> IESVS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and right deare to me in the Lord, J ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly acknowledge, that when J did obſerue the
<pb facs="tcp:19144:4"/> publike teſtimonie that God gaue to the word of his Grace, in the Sermon following, euidenced not onely by your religious attention therunto, with gracious aſpect, and long continued patience in hearing mee, for the ſpace almoſt of two houres; but alſo by the generall, and thankefull recognition of the ſame, by many, very many, of
<pb facs="tcp:19144:4"/> ſundrie ſorts, in your Citie, I did (as was meet) hereat much reioyce in ſpirit before the Lord, gaue him the glorie, and bleſſed you, in praying for you.</p>
            <p>The next day going forth into the ſtreets of your Citie, to ſee and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute ſome of my friends, I found (vpon diſcourſe) that many were deſirous to inioy the ſeruice of my
<pb facs="tcp:19144:5"/> Pen vpon this ſubiect, for their further vſe: wherewith when J had acquainted ſome of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent place, and amongst others, that learned, and graue Diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Doctor <hi>Suckling,</hi> Deane of <hi>Norwich,</hi> who hauing beene him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a hearer of me, did (I beleeue) euen out of his feeling, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, aſſure mee, that
<pb facs="tcp:19144:5"/> herein J might doe good ſeruice to God, and to his people.</p>
            <p>Vpon theſe and other Chriſtian incourageme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts I ſaid in my heart, Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this thing ſeemeth to come of the Lord, whoſe J am, and whom I ſerue in the Goſpell of his Sonne, who alſo best knowes what to doe with me, and my ſeruice. So J did (and indeed durſt
<pb facs="tcp:19144:6"/> not but) conſent, at leaſt to trie what herein the Lord would be pleaſed to doe by mee, for you. Whereupon J returning home, did ſurueigh my written Meditations, and Notes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by recouered ſome loſſes of memorie, recollected my ſpirits, and put on hard for God and his people: and by the helpe of his holy grace finiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:19144:6"/> thus this little Frame, and Jmpreſsion of the publike <hi>Seale of the Churches ſafetie.</hi> And when this weake concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my barren breſt was brought to light, by the hand of a publike profeſſed Midwife, J meane, the Printer, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring well, that as J ſtood for Father, and therefore tooke vpon me to giue it a Name, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table
<pb facs="tcp:19144:7"/> to the nature of the Matter ſubiect, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that you were to me herein in ſtead of publik Witneſſes; J hereupon eft-ſoones reſolued, that it was no leſſe reaſonable then religious for mee, when I had done with it what J would, &amp; could, to return it home againe vnto you; that ſo you might take it as your owne, poſſeſſe it, patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize
<pb facs="tcp:19144:7"/> it, and imploy it in your ſeruice, as you ſhuld thinke fit. Welcome then in gracious loue (Thou louing &amp; truly religious Citie of <hi>Norwich</hi>) this written Monument, and real Euidence of my true loue, reſpect, and thankefulneſſe to thee, &amp; thine, in Ieſus Chriſt: and let this be (as God hath appointed it) ſome weake meanes to propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
<pb facs="tcp:19144:8"/> thy Memorie, and Honor vnto Poſteritie.</p>
            <p>And now, my holy Brethren,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.1.</note> partakers of the heauenly vocation, giue me leaue vpon this occaſion, to ſpeake a good word vnto you, from the Lord our good God, in Jeſus Christ. Seeing the Lord of Heauen and Earth hath in ſpeciall mercy ſeated your free and faithfull Citie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb facs="tcp:19144:8"/> the pale of this Engliſh Paradiſe, and in the ſame doth ſtill betruſt and honor you with the vnſpeakable treaſure of his heauenly Truth, and holy Ordinances, and that in the hand of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny able, and faithfull Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, whom hee hath ſent, and ſet as bleſsings to your Citie, euen as the celeſtiall Light &amp; Salt
<pb facs="tcp:19144:9"/> of the ſame: ſeeing alſo that you doe happily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy, and ſway the Sword of ciuill Gouernement, and vnder the ſame are bleſſed with Health, Peace, Plentie, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comfortable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of life, and eſtate: And finally, ſeeing the Lord Iehouah, the great Patrone and Protector of this our Engliſh Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, hath alſo made you,
<pb facs="tcp:19144:9"/> and your Citie glorious, by great deliuerances (both in generall, and in ſpecial) from extreme dangers of vtter deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and namely, in that your ſingular preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the rage and ruines of <hi>Kets</hi> Campe, (and whiles you liue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, propagate the memorie thereof vnto your poſteritie, by a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious obſeruation of the
<pb facs="tcp:19144:10"/> time, matter, and mercy of <hi>GOD</hi> towards you therein.) Alſo in your, and our late admirable freedome from the fierie effects of that helliſh, Popiſh powder-treaſon: Let all theſe gracious &amp; ample euidences of Gods fauor, and fatherly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence to you, &amp; yours, affect, inlarge, and ſettle your Chriſtian ſoules ſo deeply in the true faith,
<pb facs="tcp:19144:10"/> feare, and loue of God, as may cauſe you to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound more and more in euery good word, and worke appertayning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you; and therein giue God the glory due to his Name, ſend in daily vnto him Tributs of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; Preſents of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, both in priuate, and publike. And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, liuing and dying, giue his holy Miniſters,
<pb facs="tcp:19144:11"/> and faithfull People, that liue with you, iuſt cauſe daily to bleſſe you in praying for you: which verily, vpon tryall, will prooue not the weakeſt way to build vp your Houſes, your Honour, and Happineſſe, both in Earth and Heauen.</p>
            <p>But leſt I ſhould ſeeme ouer-bold, or buſie with you (my good Brethren &amp; Fathers) who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:19144:11"/> do abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d with good Monitors, and doe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily carry the beſt about you in your owne breſts, I will here ſeaſonably ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpend my officious Pen, &amp; conclude with praier to God on your behalfe; That it would pleaſe his holy Maieſtie aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly to bleſſe vnto you, and yours, all the means and helps of holineſſe (and this amongst the
<pb facs="tcp:19144:12"/> reſt) which you do inioy, vntill that good worke of his Grace, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in you, ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected for the praiſe of his glorious rich Grace in Ieſus Chriſt, In whom J ſhall willingly reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours all, in all Offices of pious loue, and ſeruice, in my place and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: N. COLT.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <hi>LONDON</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the third of IVNE. 1617.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19144:12"/>
            <head>The SEALE of the CHVRCHES ſafetie, &amp;c.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. PET. 2.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord hath knowne to deliuer the godly out of temptation: and to reſerue the vniuſt to the day of iudgement to be puniſhed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen this ſolemne taske of ſacred du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was lately put vpon mee by the hand of publike Authoritie, (which I haue reaſon much to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19144:13"/> reſpect) though the lets both publike and priuate which did wreſtle with mee in the Worke, were neyther few, nor weake; yet perceiuing that my calling hereunto was not vncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I reſolued with Chriſtian confidence herein to caſt my ſelfe wholly vpon the helpe of <hi>Heauen,</hi> both for <hi>Theame, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, and Matter,</hi> that in ſome meaſure might be ſutable to the <hi>occaſion,</hi> and to this ſolemne <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein notwithſtanding, I doe humbly craue of all ſorts a friendly, both conſtruction, and acceptation of that plaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of holy Truth, which by Gods aſſiſtance, I ſhall deliuer vnto you out of this ſacred and ſweet <hi>Oracle;</hi> within the limits whereof lye two grand <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions:</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19144:13"/> One of admirable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndleſſe comfort to the Godly;<note place="margin">The parts and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text.</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he other</hi> of no leſſe horrour and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onfuſion to all the world of the wicked. The former of theſe is deliuered in forme of a <hi>Promiſe:</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he latter of a <hi>Threatning.</hi> In both we are to conſider the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and the <hi>Thing.</hi> In the former <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Perſon</hi> promiſing <hi>[the Lord]</hi> and the parties to whom the promiſe is made <hi>[the Godly] Then the thing promiſed, [which is Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance]</hi> which is amplified and made lightſome. Firſt, by the cauſe thereof <hi>[the knowledge of God,] [the Lord knoweth]</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, by the kinde of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance <hi>[out of tentation.]</hi> So then wee haue in the former paſſage, Firſt, the <hi>Authour of this benefit, the Lord.</hi> Secondly, the <hi>Efficient</hi> cauſe and ground thereof, <hi>his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19144:14"/> knowledge, [The Lord knoweth.]</hi> Thirdly, the <hi>benefit</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>[De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance.]</hi> Fourthly, the <hi>Obiect,</hi> or parties vpon whom the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit is conferred <hi>[the godly.]</hi> And laſtly, the <hi>kind</hi> of the benefit be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed <hi>[deliuerance out of tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.]</hi> The <hi>reſolution</hi> of the other part of this <hi>Sentence</hi> agreeth with this in effect; And thus much of the <hi>Methode</hi> plainely and briefly.</p>
            <p>Now, although I know that the Learned amongſt you, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not neceſſarily expect any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations touching matter of Inference, Reference, Connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Dependance that ſhould lye betweene this <hi>Period</hi> and the Premiſes, ſeeing in the originall there is neyther Relatiue, Illa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue, nor Copulatiue particle to be found: yet becauſe indeed it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19144:14"/> is ſo, I will ſay that this <hi>Sentence</hi> is the <hi>Concluſion</hi> of a former <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction,</hi> and ſo both in <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi> doth depend vpon the Premiſes. Which thing, further to manifeſt, let vs make ſome ſhort <hi>Suruey</hi> of that which went before in this Chap. where you ſhall find that the holy Apoſtle hauing in the end of the former Chapter ſet forth the certainetie, and dignitie of the Doctrine of of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> both from the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour thereof,</hi> and from the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that it hath with the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> doth vpon this occaſion, in the beginning of this Chapter tell the Church (as <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe did, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. and <hi>Paul,</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.) That in theſe laſt times there ſhould ariſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Falſe-Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Falſe-Teachers,</hi> that ſhould <hi>bring in</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19144:15"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>damnable Hereſies,</hi> (in effect) to the denying of <hi>the Lord that bought them;</hi> and (yet) that many <hi>ſhould follow their damnable wayes: by whom the way of Truth ſhould be ill-ſpoken of, &amp;c.</hi> And that they through curſed couetouſneſſe and baſe<note n="e" place="margin">Multos fore eorum ſectatores. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> flatterie ſhould make<note n="f" place="margin">Quàm vera &amp; viua eſt haec Romani Cleri deſcriptio: Beza.</note> marchandize of <hi>Soules.</hi> For all which their wickednes (ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) they ſhall bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelues<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſwift deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which deſtruction hee doth not onely denounce againſt them by the <hi>Spirit of Prophecie,</hi> as it were by diuine Diuination; but alſo prooueth it by Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall demonſtration: namely, by an Induction of ſundry particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars of Gods Iuſtice inflicted vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both <hi>Angels,</hi> and <hi>Men,</hi> which formerly had ſinned againſt the Lord. <hi>For</hi> (ſayth the Apoſtle)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19144:15"/> 
               <hi>if God did not ſpare the Angels which ſinned, nor the olde World, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or Sodome and Gomorrha,</hi> ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her will he ſpare theſe, &amp;c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this <hi>Conſequence</hi> is wanting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the Greeke, but by a<note n="a" place="margin">Ellipſis conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Figure frequent in Holy Scripture, is to bee vnderſtood neceſſarily, and ſupplyed, as it is in the margent.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, beſides this <hi>Induction</hi> of particulars, the Apoſtle for further proofe of their vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted puniſhment, doth vſe two ſtrong Arguments to euince the ſame; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the one taken from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie and<note n="b" place="margin">A pari.</note> identitie of Diuine Iuſtice, which is euer the ſame, when the caſe is alike. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The other Argument is taken from the <note n="c" place="margin">A maiori.</note> greater to the leſſe, if wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the excellencie of Angels aboue men. This done; the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to theſe inſtances of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19144:16"/> Iuſtice, addeth (as a <hi>Corallary</hi> of comfort to Gods Elect,) two famous Examples of ſpeciall mercie from God, ſhewed in the preſeruation of <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot, verſes</hi> 5.6.7.8. From all which Monuments of Diuine Iuſtice, and Mercie, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> inferreth this <hi>Concluſion,</hi> and Diuine <hi>Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme, The Lord knoweth to deliuer the godly, &amp;c. and to reſerue the wicked to, &amp;c.</hi> And thus much of the<note n="d" place="margin">Series oratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum.</note> thread of ſpeech, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of matter, and depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of this ſacred <hi>Concluſion,</hi> inferred vpon that which went before in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>Now let vs come to make ſome vſe of the Apoſtles order, and kinde of confirmation. It is by an inartificiall <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> commonly called<note n="e" place="margin">Inductio eſt argumentatio à pluribus parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularibus ad v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſale, quaſi à partibus ad to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum progreſſio, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Induction,</hi> or <hi>Enumeration of Particulars</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19144:16"/> a generall truth of that kind: as for example, if a man by this kind of reaſoning would proue <hi>Iuſtification by faith</hi> againſt a Papiſt; let him doe it by an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> of <hi>Particulars,</hi> and ſay;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel was iustified by Faith, ſo was Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Iſaac, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Moſes, &amp;c.</hi> Neyther can you find the<note n="f" place="margin">Nec in caeteris contrarium, eſt videre: ergo, &amp;c.</note> contrary in any of the Saints of God, <hi>Therefore, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is iuſtified, is iustified by Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One <hi>Inſtance</hi> more, againſt the confident ſinner his vaine hope of Saluation. As if you would prooue, that without true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance he cannot be ſaued; argue thus, by an <hi>Induction</hi> of particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and ſay; that neyther <hi>Dauid,</hi> nor <hi>Peter,</hi> nor <hi>Zacheus,</hi> nor <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> nor <hi>Paul,</hi> nor the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtuous <hi>Corinthian,</hi> without true repentance could be ſaued, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19144:17"/> is the contrarie to be found in the Booke of God: therefore without true repentance no man can be ſaued.</p>
            <p>Loe, this is a ſure and ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied kind of reaſoning, in caſes of Religion; and is both Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Theologicall, I meane, both Naturall, and Spirituall, Humane, and Diuine; fit both for Learned, and Vnlearned to vſe for their Inſtruction, Conui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Confirmation, Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c. And for this cauſe alſo among other ends, (as I beleeue) it hath pleaſed God in his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar wiſdome and mercie to leau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vpon Record in his Holy Word ſo many examples of both good and bad; and of their different eſtates and ends.</p>
            <p>And ſo let vs now proceede from the Apoſtle his <hi>Order</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19144:17"/> 
               <hi>Inference,</hi> modeſtly to ſurueigh and ſearch his <hi>Euidence,</hi> touching the <hi>Safe-conduct</hi> and <hi>Protection</hi> of all the godly, in the middeſt of all ſtraits, dangers, tryalls, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, euils, and enemies, vntill ſuch time as they bee ſafely arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the Kingdome of <hi>Heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The warrant and <hi>Euidence</hi> that the Apoſtle here ſheweth for it, is this, <hi>[That the Lord doth know how to deliuer his, &amp;c.]</hi> Out of which wordes I purpoſe (though ſparingly, as I paſſe through them) to giue you in the firſt place, ſome Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Punctuall <hi>Obſeruations;</hi> (yet not to ſhew my ſelfe; that vanitie were too light for the grauitie of a Diuine, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelfe and his ſeruice to be ſubiect to a ſtrict <hi>Triall</hi> before Gods <hi>Tribunall,</hi> but) to ſhew you
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19144:18"/> in part what hidden Myſteries of Diuinitie lye folded vp, not onely in <hi>compleat Sentences,</hi> but alſo in the <hi>ſingle words of Sacred Writ.</hi> In the next place you ſhall haue ſuch Poſitions, and Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations, both for Doctrine, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Comfort, as I can collect fitly, out of this heauenly Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle.</p>
            <p>I find in the Booke of GOD, that the word <hi>(Lord)</hi> when it is applyed vnto God indefinitely, is to bee taken two-wayes; that is to ſay, ſometimes<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Eſſentially,</hi> and ſometimes<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Poſſeſsiuely.</hi> For the former, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. <hi>The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is made to you</hi> (ſayth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Peter</hi> to the <hi>Iewes) and to your children, and to all that are a farre off, euen to as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> For the latter, read <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25. <hi>I thanke
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19144:18"/> thee</hi> (or as the Greeke word is, I confeſſe vnto thee) <hi>O Father,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Lord of Heauen and Earth, &amp;c. Poſſeſsiuely taken.</hi> So likewiſe, the Greeke word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>[Lord]</hi> may (I ſuppoſe) admit a two-fold deriuation, <hi>videlicet,</hi> it may come eyther of the <hi>Verbe</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or the <hi>Nowne</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the former ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be the firſt<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Ens aeternum.</note> 
               <hi>Eſſence,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the firſt<note n="l" place="margin">Ens Entium, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Authour;</hi> and ſo may paralell that eſſentiall name of God, <hi>Iehouah</hi>] who is an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite and vnſearchable <hi>Selfe-being Eſſence,</hi> eternall, euerlaſting, and vnchangeable, giuing being and beginning to all things, &amp;c. Or elſe it may come of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſo ſhould intimate the poſſeſſing and gouerning of all things, as abſolute Lord, Owner, and Commander of them: and ſo it anſwereth to the Hebrew word
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19144:19"/> 
               <hi>Bagnal, Hoſ.</hi> 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of-him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe-Lord, ſimply and abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as he alone that hath abſolute and vniuerſall power, in, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all things, cauſes, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoeuer, whereſoeuer.</p>
            <p>And this of the deriuation, &amp; ſenſe of the firſt word (Lord) taken either eſſentially or poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely: here you may ſafely take it in both ſenſes, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to either.</p>
            <p>The doctrine, and duties to be deriued from hence, I deferre, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I haue ſpoken of the Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie of the next word, and then will I proſecute them together ioyntly and ſeuerally. It follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Text, <hi>The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, &amp;c.]</hi> The greeke word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] which anſwereth to the hebrew word <hi>Iadang]</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> which (as Scholers know) doth ſignifie to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19144:19"/> be much, and long acquainted with the thing which we know; as here now to import thus much,<note place="margin">Longo vſu exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citatus &amp; in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berandis pijs, &amp; in puniendis ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leratis, Beza.</note> 
               <hi>That the Lord hath beene long time exerciſed and accuſtomed with the both deliuering and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the godly; and with puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wicked.</hi> And in this very ſenſe, and in the like ſubiect doth the holy Prophet, <hi>Pſal</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 6. vſe the ſame word; where hauing ſhewed the different conditions, eſtate, and end of the good and bad, he concludeth with this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation: for <hi>the Lord knoweth the way of the righteous, and the way of the wicked,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ki-iodeang Iehouah derec tſaddikim vederecreſchagnim tobedh.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The greeke tongue ſeemeth to diſtinguiſh the three kindes of common knowledge, <hi>ſenſual, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional,</hi> and <hi>artificial,</hi> I meane, of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19144:20"/> Senſe, of Reaſon, and of Art, by three ſeuerall words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, outſtrips them all, and addeth vnto the three former a fourth kinde of knowledge, namely, experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. In which kinde it may be, that the holy Angels themſelues increaſe in knowledge, experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally.</p>
            <p>But howſoeuer the rules goe with Creatures, and with their knowledge; I am ſure that it go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth far otherwiſe with the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, whoſe knowledge is (as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe) infinite, and vnſearchable. Inſomuch as, me thinkes, I heare the holy Apoſtle here proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming openly, that <hi>there is nothing ſo darke, deepe, or difficult, ſo large and manifold, which hath beene, is, or can be hid from the ancient, perfect, and plenarie knowledge of the Lord
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19144:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> God, with whom we haue to doe, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.</note> Moreouer, finding the <hi>verb</hi> here vſed, to be put in the <hi>tenſe</hi> and <hi>time</hi> paſt (for punie Scholers know, that it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) and therfore ſhould be read <hi>[The Lord hath known]</hi> it ſheweth that this knowledge of GOD our Lord is from euerlaſting, to euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting; no time paſt, preſent, or to come, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> determine his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but it farre farre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all terme of time.</p>
            <p>Now from all theſe punctuall impreſſions of this word of truth, let me collect, &amp; giue vnto you ſome weak definition of the knowledge of God, thus: <hi>The knowledge of God is that, by which the Lord our God in one eternall, &amp; ineffable act of infinite vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, doth diſtinctly and perfectly know all things, perſons, cauſes, times
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19144:21"/> and occurrences, which haue beene, are, or ſhall be more and leſſe, first and laſt, together with all their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, quantities, qualities, inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, motions, actions, and ends; and this, not by certayne degrees, and paſſages, nor by obſeruations, and notions abſtracted, and taken from the things themſelues (as Men and Angels may know things:)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nil Creatoris aut lateat cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitionem, aut effugiat poteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Aug.</note> 
               <hi>but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially, of, in, and from himſelfe, abſolutely, ſimply, and all at once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which <hi>his abſolute diuine knowledge of all things</hi> is ioyned <hi>his infinite Act of will,</hi> whereby God willeth them freely, iuſtly, eternally, and vnchangeably; and according to the ſame doth effectually, preciſely, punctual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and fully performe the ſame his knowledge and will in all things euermore: &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and by name in theſe two
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19144:21"/> mayne parts of his moſt holy Will, and decree of preſeruing and deliuering his faithful-ones, the godly; and of reſeruing the wicked to the day of iudgment, to be puniſhed, as here in our Text is proclaymed.</p>
            <p>And if here we may be bold to take in that ancient and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe principle in diuinitie, <hi>That all the eſſentiall attributes of God</hi> (whereof his knowledge is one) doe agree,<note place="margin">Attributa Dei eſſentialia, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſingulis diuinitatis Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonis competunt.</note> and equally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to all the perſons of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Trinitie; then it muſt needes follow that this is truly teſtified of God the Father, of God the Sonne, and of God the holy Ghoſt, that they equally, and ioyntly, ſeuerally, infallibly and eternally doe know (with which knowledge is ioyned <hi>Will, Power,</hi> and <hi>Effect</hi>) how to deliuer the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19144:22"/> godly out of, &amp;c. Oh ſweet, oh precious, oh ſauing knowledge of the glorious Godhead in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie &amp; Vnitie thus concurring, thus co-working for the Elects well-fare! Now then to this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God, and ſoueraigne Lord, Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, one and the ſame God in nature, and number, God ouer all, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for euer, be all all honor, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, faith, loue, feare, obedience, &amp; praiſe yeelded by vs, by ours, and by all his redeemed, eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Amen, Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this truth doe the holy Prophets &amp; Apoſtles beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Reade <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. throughout, and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. &amp;c. But moſt pregnant for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is that place <hi>Act.</hi> 15.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>v.</hi> 18. where the Apoſtle <hi>Iames</hi> auouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that all the workes of God
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19144:22"/> are knowne to him from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. And as knowne, ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are they ordered. For ſaith our Apoſtle, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.6. <hi>It is he that worketh all in all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tripliciter ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur Deus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Suidas.</note> [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] The anomie, diſorder, and euill of the action God permitteth; the action it ſelf God ordereth. In good creatures God worketh his will not onely by them, but alſo in them; as in <hi>Dauid, &amp;c.</hi> In the reſt, not in them, yet by them: as in <hi>Iudas, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs now at length come to make ſome vſe (by way of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and obſeruation) both of the abſolute ſoueraigntie of our God, as he is Lord; and alſo of his infinite knowledge, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, which (as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſaith) <hi>doth equally reach vnto all things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to euery haire of euery head,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19144:23"/> and to euery bird of euery fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>And ſith the Apoſtle 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. affirmeth, that the right vſe of all holy truth is <hi>to teach, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue, to correct, &amp; inſtruct in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe]</hi> we will haue ſome eye vnto the ſame in our applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>And firſt, foraſmuch as the Lord <hi>Iehouah,</hi> who, properly to ſpeake, is Lord onely, doth of right (as you haue heard) chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to himſelfe full, abſolute, and vniuerſall Power in, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all things, perſons, &amp;c. let vs all learne alwayes, and in euery eſtate, thus to acknowledge him to be our Lord and our God; yea, let the greateſt Lords, and higheſt Powers vpon earth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that their places, &amp; power are of &amp; from this Lord, and being deriued from him, are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19144:23"/> dependant vpon him, limitted by him, and ſubiect vnto him; and conſequently, that they muſt bee countable vnto him in a moſt ſtrict account. For ſayth King <hi>Salomon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sap. cap. <hi>6.3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The rule is giuen you of the Lord, and your Power by the moſt High, which will trie your workes, and ſearch out your imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, &amp;c.</hi> Turne not therfore your power and places of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie into carnall Pompe, or priuate gaine, much leſſe into perſonall reuenge and cruel op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; but with holy <hi>Dauid</hi> ſing <hi>Mercie and Iudgement to the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101.</note> For you exerciſe but a Miniſterie of Iuſtice, and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, vnder his holy Maieſtie; and not any abſolute, diſſolute, law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Authoritie, which is little better then plaine tyrannie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſeeing this high
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19144:24"/> and holy Lord of heauen and earth, giueth this ſubordinate Power to men; let vs, and all, learne to obey them in the Lord that doe command and rule ouer vs in the Lord,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.2.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and that for Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, let vs all from hence learne, that we are not our own, nor any thing that we haue, is abſolutely ours, but the Lords; and therefore, that our ſelues, and all that wee haue, ought to beat his command in all things, times &amp; eſtates, and ſo to make all ſerue for his honour and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, cheerefully, conſcionably, conſtantly.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſith we are all<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſeruants vnder one and the ſame Soueraigne Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, howſoeuer otherwiſe wee differ in place, and partes, office,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19144:24"/> and adminiſtration; yet let no man lift vp his heart aboue that which is meet, but in loue learne to ſerue, helpe, and honour one another in the Lord, as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth fellow-ſeruants, that are equally intereſſed in the Title and honour of the heauenly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, let vs (with theſe heads of duetie) conſider our dignitie, and ſafetie vnder the Shield, and ſauing Power of this our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord and God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort our ſelues in the ſame, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all the baſeneſſe of our out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward eſtate, and contempt of the world: alſo vnder the enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and hoſtilitie of Sathan and of ſinners, of Pope, or Papiſt: and ſing we a ſweete and ſacred <hi>Requiem,</hi> and Al-hayle to our bleſſed King, Queene, Prince,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19144:25"/> State, our ſelues and ours, ſo long as GOD is our Lord, and wee continue his faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants in Ieſus Chriſt. Care and feare be remoued from vs: and let heauenly comfort and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence accompanie vs, vntill we haue finiſhed our courſe in the faith &amp; ſeruice of the Lord our God, euen of this Lord that knoweth how to deliuer all his from euill, and to bring them to neuer-ending Honour.</p>
            <p>And thus may wee profit by the knowledge and faith of this point, that God is the Lord, our Lord, abſolute in Power, glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in praiſes, doing wonders; wonders (I ſay) for his ſeruants ſafetie, as appeareth in vs this day. <hi>Oh how bleſſed are the people whoſe God is the Lord Iehouah, euen the people whom he hath choſen for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19144:25"/> his Inheritance, Pſa.</hi> 33. So much of the firſt word in our Text. Now let vs come to make ſome vſe of the next head of doctrine, touching the knowledge of this Lord, <hi>[The Lord knoweth.]</hi> The Atheiſt beleeueth not the truth of this Text; but ſaith, Is there any ſuch knowledge in the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie? Others hold the Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nims principle, that tho God knoweth all, yet ſay, <hi>Non vacat Ioui, &amp;c.</hi> The Lord hath no lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to attend vpon euery trifle; which one thus well anſwereth, <hi>That as God vouchſafed to create the leaſt and baſest things:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sicut non dede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit Deum infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma creare, ſic nec creata cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare.</note> 
               <hi>ſo hee diſdaineth not to regard, and order the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The common ſort of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans will bee brought to yeelde (perhaps) that the Lord vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth and knoweth all, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19144:26"/> potentially is able to doe what hee will: but hardly can bee brought to confeſſe a particular and practike knowledge in God, which extendeth it ſelfe to all and euery leaſt creature, &amp; thing whatſoeuer vnder heauen, in heauen. Yet muſt euen this alſo be beleeued, or elſe this <hi>Truth of doctrine</hi> (which is the ground of our hope and ſafetie) <hi>is violated.</hi> Finally, the weake Chriſtian, which yet is not wholly voide of faith in God, not duely pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering this point of holy truth, ſeeing the proſperity of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the affliction of the good, doth thereupon conceiue amiſſe of the Lord his gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and knowledge of things here below; and ſo alſo becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth impatient, and heartleſſe, to his owne great hurt, and the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19144:26"/> offence of Heauen. All theſe muſt learne to know and beleeue (if they will bee ſaued) that in God our Lord, aſſuredly there is an eternall, abſolute, and infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible knowledge of all things whatſoeuer; together with wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, will, and power to rule, order, and diſpoſe of them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, vntill euery thing be brought to that period and end which he hath appointed for his owne glory, the ſaluation of the Elect, and ruine of the Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate rout. For the holy Word of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lord doth here witneſſe the ſame, and his holy workes doe confirme it abundantly.</p>
            <p>Now, the meditation of all that herein hath beene ſaid, and truely taught out of theſe two words ioyned together, <hi>The Lord knoweth]</hi> referred to both the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19144:27"/> parts of this <hi>Prophecy,</hi> as the ſame ought to be, might (me thinkes) ſtrike a ſtrange terrour into the ſoule of any ſinner, (which is not too too forlone, and harde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in ſinne) when he ſhal come to himſelfe, and conſider that hee hath ſinned againſt a Lord,</p>
            <p>Firſt, of infinite knowledge, which perfectly knoweth the number and nature of all his ſinnes whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of infinite Iuſtice, and therefore cannot let eſcape the leaſt particular ſinne which he was euer guiltie of, originally, or perſonally; vnleſſe hee find mercie in the <hi>Mediatour,</hi> vpon his true repentance, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conuerſion <hi>from the power of Satan, to the liuing Lord, and from the diſobedience of the wicked, to the wiſedome of the iuſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19144:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Thirdly, of infinite power alſo, and authoritie <hi>to caſt both ſoule and bodie into Hell-fire,</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually, vnrecouerably.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, of infinite Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to giue the impenitent ſinner eternitie in that vnſpeakeable miſerie.</p>
            <p>Oh, conſider this, all that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get God, together with his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable knowledge, power and iuſtice! Make vp your peace with GOD in time; in time (I ſay) <hi>lest he teare you in pieces, and there bee none to deliuer you out of his hand; that knoweth how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue (not preſerue) the wicked to Iudgement, to be puniſhed eternally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, let me tell you (as I verily beleeue) that the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, vnbeliefe, or obliuion of this holy Truth, that GOD knoweth abſolutely all things,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19144:28"/> euen all ſecrets of all mens mindes, and manners; and that hee hath abſolute power in and ouer all, as the Lord of Lords; the ignorance, I ſay, and vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of this truth is the maine cauſe, and root of all <hi>Atheiſme, Prophaneneſſe, Hypocriſie, Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> and (to come neerer the point in hand) of all ſinnefull feare, and deſpaire in dangers and diſtreſſe; alſo of carnall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, ſinnefull ſecuritie, and ſhifting by corrupt courſes, to helpe our ſelues in time of need: alſo of all baſe, groſſe and weake conceits of God, and of his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment: and finally of all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiencie, murmuring, &amp;c. vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affliction.</p>
            <p>Whereas on the contrarie, the ſound and ſanctified know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of GODS infinite power
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19144:28"/> and wiſdome to performe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he will, and hath reuealed in his Word, will helpe to afford all good Chriſtians vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble animation, affiance, loue, awe, peace, patience, conſtancy, and comfort to caſt all their cares, and burthen vpon the Lord (as hee hath commanded) and ſo to reſt in peace and ſacred ſecuritie, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Finally, (that I may grow to an end in the application of this firſt part of the Text,) ſeeing <hi>the Lord bringeth his iudgements to light euery morning,</hi> as his holy Word doth witneſſe (in his knowledge and power perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ſame) let vs learne hence-forth to make due and daily obſeruation thereof; that wee may ſay, as <hi>Thuſidides</hi> did in another caſe; <hi>I haue experience
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19144:29"/> of this and that Truth of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled eyther in mercie or iustice:</hi> &amp; ſo ioyne experimentall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and faith with literall and ſpirituall. How many Chriſtians continue weake in faith and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience! &amp;c. becauſe they bee wanting this way to God in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>(for God hath ſo done his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailous workes, that they ought to be had in remembrance)</hi> and to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in wiſedome.</p>
            <p>Neglect not then this helpe of holineſſe, if you would grow vp faſter in all holy feare, faith, loue, and obedience, &amp;c. Learne alſo this leſſon of all the wiſe-hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Patriarchs, Prophets, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Lord his people;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.37.</note> 
               <hi>ſpecially of holy Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. <hi>48.7.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>in his bleſſed Booke of Pſalmes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo let vs proceede in the Text to the next word <hi>[Deliuer]
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19144:29"/> The Lord knoweth to deliuer.]</hi> This is one ſingular effect of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Cauſe, [Deliuerance to the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.]</hi> The knowledge of God is neyther idle, nor vnfruitfull; but operatiue, and effectuall: and that vnto theſe two ends princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally, ſo farre forth as it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Man: namely, to ſaue the godly, and to wrecke the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. And of theſe, becauſe the ſaluation of the iuſt is of ſpecial conſequence for the glorie of <hi>Gods ſauing power, and Fatherly Prouidence,</hi> therefore it is here ſet in the firſt place, and hath the preeminence. And a ſingular Preſident (mee thinkes) it is of good Gouernment, and of the right vſe of all that knowledge, and power wherewith the Lord hath furniſhed vs, or any of vs, whether we be Magiſtrates, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19144:30"/> or Maſters of Families. In the extent of mercie and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Firſt, to bee guided by knowledge, euen by Diuine knowlege and vnderſtanding of Gods will: Secondly, to limit it by the power and place which wee hold in charge: Thirdly, ſpecially, and aboue the reſt, to doe good to the good, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and deliuer the Iuſt, ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them that ſhould be ſaued in the firſt place. Let <hi>Noah</hi> bee firſt ſhipped in ſafetie in GODS <hi>Arke,</hi> before the flouds of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ouerflow the World. And let <hi>Lot</hi> be gone from <hi>Sodome</hi> (y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Angels of the Lord) before yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> fire the place of his Repoſe.</p>
            <p>Conſider what I haue ſayd and the Lord giue you vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things to doe his will. And thus much briefely o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19144:30"/> the connexion of the effect with the cauſe, and of the Apoſtles order in putting the ſafety of the Saints in the firſt place, and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of Gods moſt holy Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Againe, further obſerue here with me, that the Lord our God taketh the ground of his doing good to his ſeruants, euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom his owne eternall, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable knowledge, wil, and goodneſſe; which worketh free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y of it ſelfe, and from it ſelfe, all the effects of mercie, and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion promiſed to his Saints.</p>
            <p>Let then our helpe alſo, and ſeruice which wee yeeld to the people of God in our places, not be baſe, inforced, mercinarie, or any way corrupt at the root; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngenuous, free, and faithfull; that ſo we may (in our meaſure) become merciful and iuſt, as our
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19144:31"/> heauenly Father is to vs.</p>
            <p>The Text followeth, <hi>[The Lord knoweth to deliuer.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The word here vſed, doth properly ſignifie to take by force,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, h. e. Eripere. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and to deliuer with ſtrong hand: as if the Apoſtle ſhould tell all the <hi>godly,</hi> that otherwiſe all euils and enemies, dangers &amp; diſtreſſes would hold them, euen with might &amp; main in durance, and in bondage, <hi>videlicet,</hi> if the Lord ſhould not ſtep forth with force to reſcue, and deliuer them out of all: as of old he deliuered his beloued <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this then wee are aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of many things, worthy on conſideration. As firſt, to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what is the naturall properti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and practice of euill things, and perſons, yea, and of their fathe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Deuill, as Chriſt our LORD
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19144:31"/> ſpeaketh, <hi>Iohn</hi> 8. namely, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to hurt, and to hold vnder the bondage of affliction, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, and death, all the godly, euen the good and faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Lord; and hereunto will bend all their ſtrength of wit, will, power, &amp;c. Inſomuch as the Lord our good GOD is faine to arme himſelfe with power, euen with a ſtrong hand and ſtretched out arme (often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) to deliuer them; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that which is written in the <hi>Pſalme,</hi> 37.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.</note> 
               <hi>The Saluation of the righteous commeth of the Lord, who is alſo their ſtrength in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ime of trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, and conſequently, being hereby admoniſhed to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend on the one ſide our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall danger, and on the other ſide our ignorance to diſcerne,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19144:32"/> and weakeneſſe to decline the ſame, wee muſt learne to walke the more wiſely, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectly, to ſtand vpon our Gard, to keepe <hi>Sentinell,</hi> and continuall watch, to arme our ſelues, as the holy Word forewarneth in the fifth and ſixth Chapters of the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians:</hi> And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, in humilitie, faith, feeling, and true thankefulneſſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, and ſay with the <hi>Pſalmist, All our helpe, hope, comfort, and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation ſtandeth in the name, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, mercie, power, and goodneſſe of the Lord our God, the God of our ſtrength, hope and happineſſe; which hath made, and doth rule both heauen and earth.</hi> Laſtly, we are herein taught, that there is no ſtrength, power, or wiſedome againſt the Lord, or againſt his Seruants ſafetie. <hi>My Father is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19144:32"/> ſtronger then all, and no man can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake out of his hand,</hi> ſayth our bleſſed Sauiour, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>That the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe of God is ſtronger then men:]</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ea then all men and Deuils. Care and feare away then with Gods Elect. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.] For the Lord, euen our Lord, knoweth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow with force to cruſh our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oes, that otherwiſe would cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y crucifie vs &amp; al our comforts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that, no leſſe outragiouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen the <hi>Iewes</hi> did <hi>Ieſus</hi> our Lord; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r then the Ieſuites and Papiſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Liſt would haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one our deare and dread So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eraigne, &amp;c. as you ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eare more at large anon in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt place, and paſſage of our Sermon.</p>
            <p>It followeth in the Text <hi>[The
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19144:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lord hath knowne to deliuer the godly.]</hi> The ſtate of the caſe in hand (you ſee) concerneth them that are godly; all them: none elſe. Impietie hath no part in Gods protection heere promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: the vngodly perſon is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred from this ſaluation. The word here vſed is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which commeth of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>colere,</hi> which doth ſignifie both to haue one in high eſtimation and honour, and alſo to affect and loue in ſpeciall maner and meaſure. Of this roote and primitiue <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> commeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the nownes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Engliſh one truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, another irreligious, a third ſuperſtitious. And to theſe three ſortes you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all that liue in the viſible Church: but the <hi>Accent</hi> is ſet
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19144:33"/> vpon the head of the godly. <hi>For the Lord hath choſen to himſelfe the Man that is godly, Pſal.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>But you will aske me, Who be they whom the Apoſtle cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth godly? I anſwer; and marke it well: <hi>The godly are they that rightly know the true God, and doe duely worſhip him in Ieſus Christ.</hi> Or take it thus, Whoſoeuer tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knoweth, or endeuoureth to know, loue, feare and obey the true God, in the faith of Chriſt, is indeede godly in the account of <hi>Heauen,</hi> whoſe part is in this, and in all the promiſes of grace and ſaluation recorded in holy writ. And ſeeing this point is of ſo great importance, giue me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaue yet further to lay it open vnto you, that you may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſcerne of the thing, and of your eſtate thereby.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19144:34"/>
            <p>To know God aright (which is the ground of true godlynes) is to know and acknowledge him as he hath reuealed himſelfe vnto vs in his holy word, and in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in this knowledge to cleaue vnto God in the faith and loue of his holy Maieſtie, as to our onely Lord God in Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in the life of this knowledge, faith, and loue to ſerue, obey, and honour the Lord by doing his will, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the meaſure of Grace that we haue receiued, humbly, ſincerely, cheerefully, prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conſtantly.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>Looke vpon the man, or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that is indeede partaker of the godly Nature (not Eſſence) more plainely to ſay, that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19144:34"/> by the ſpirit of grace, and ſtandeth in the ſtate of grace, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and ſanctified in Ieſus Chriſt (for this is the partie that the Apoſtle intendeth to bee pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) looke (I ſay) vpon his, or her diſpoſition, affections, and meditations, as they doe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt themſelues, (for they can not lie long hid where indeede they are:) marke alſo their ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, prayers, actions, ſufferings, trials, comforts, and triumphs in life, and in death, and you ſhal finde them all more, or leſſe ſeaſoned with faith, pietie and the feare of God, with zeale of his glorie, humilitie, repentance, patience, hope, and ioy in the holy Ghoſt. Euen thus ſhal you finde the godly qualified, and ſanctified in heart and life, reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely ſet to walke with God; as
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19144:35"/> others are diſſolutely diſpoſed to walke like themſelues, with the world,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>In the luſt of the eye, in the luſts of the fleſh, or in the pride of life:</hi> That is, in the loue and deſires of worldly Profit, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or Preferment, ſome be ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with this, ſome with that carnall delight: not any ſinner (lightly) with all; but all with ſome one of theſe; which is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough without radicall Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, to ſequeſter them for euer from the hope, and helpe of this and all other bleſſings promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the godly.</p>
            <p>Thus then you ſee (in part) how precious, and profitable a thing true pietie is: by which all things muſt be ſquared, our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and doings; our, and your ſpeeches, pleaſures, and very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell muſt bee ſuch as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19144:35"/> true godlyneſſe, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.10. there called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: which the Apoſtle ſaith, is profitable for all things, times, eſtates, and purpoſes; as that which <hi>hath the promiſes of this life, and of that which is to</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now then to ſpeake comfortably to all that are true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly religious and godly, though it bee but in the beginnings and infancy of the true feare of God: Behold how the holy Ghoſt in the writings of the Sanctuarie, (which are our Euidence for our heauenly inheritance,) dooth grace you with Titles of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of honour. You are ſtiled <hi>The children of light, of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, of obedience, and of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; a royall Priesthood, a holy Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, a peculiar People, anointed, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted, and ſealed to the day of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption;
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19144:36"/> the ſeruants, friends, and children of the euerliuing God; heires, &amp; fellow heires with Chriſt, heires of Grace, of life, of glorie, of heauen: holy, iuſt, mercifull, good, and godly, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doth Heauen thus heape Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vpon you? and doe you yet droope, and hang down the head vnder the contempt of the World? you are moſt happie and honourable in the ſight of God, and his Angels; and yet you cannot ſee into it, through the filthy fogs of the worlds va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porous words. Let me tell you in loue, that you are much to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> blame thus to wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g your ſelues But I will leaue you a while to your ſecond and wiſer cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and will turne me (as you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Aduocate) to pleade your cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a little with the men of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19144:36"/> world, and plainely tell them, that if they will not in time learne of God in his word how to thinke and ſpeake louingly, and reſpectiuely of his Sonnes and Daughters, but will needes goe on ſtill to ouer-caſt their brightnes with clouds of ſcorn, &amp; to blemiſh their beautie with termes of reproach: there is a day comming (and it makes haſte vpon them) <hi>When the Lord will ſpeake to them in his wrath, and vexe them in his ſore diſpleaſure, Pſal.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>I reade in the booke of <hi>Ester, cap.</hi> 8. that when the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> did ſee how the Lord God did deliuer and bleſſe his people <hi>Iſrael,</hi> many thereupon became <hi>Iewes,</hi> turned <hi>Iewes,</hi> as the phraſe is now, turned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. O happy turne &amp; change!
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19144:37"/> So could I wiſh that Papiſts, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, and all other euill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed perſons would, vpon the knowledge of the great honor and happineſſe of the Saints and true Seruants of God, be moued thereby to turne Saints; that is, to become godly and holy men, and women; without which, they cannot be ſaued. For all ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation is intayled by the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace in Chriſt, to the Saints, and to their holy Seede, <hi>Who haue obtayned like precious faith with vs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>through the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, as it is,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1.</p>
            <p>To proceede now (in the laſt place) to the kind of deliuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, which, in this heauenly Oracle is promiſed to all the godly: it is (ſaith the Text) from temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The word in the Greeke is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19144:37"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as the hebrew word is <hi>Maſſa,</hi> of <hi>Naſah.</hi> Now we find that in holy Scripture <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations</hi> are of two ſorts,<note place="margin">Two ſorts of Temptations, <hi>viz.</hi> Of
<list>
                     <item>Sinne,</item>
                     <item>Sorrow.</item>
                  </list>
               </note> and ſo the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Temptation</hi>] hath a twofold conſtruction. For firſt, there be temptations of ſin &amp; ſinners; from which we pray (in the Lords prayer) and God hath promiſed to deliuer his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect in Chriſt; namely, from the curſe, and power of them, in that degree, and meaſure, which God knoweth meet for his glorie.<note place="margin">Gradibus qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, &amp;c.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, there be Temptations of ſorrow, trouble, affliction, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; diſtreſſe, which God ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto his Saints, either as trials, or chaſtiſements, or both. In this latter ſenſe the word <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> is to be taken in this place. For ſo ſhall the Concluſion pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralell the Premiſſes, that is, This
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19144:38"/> generall promiſe of deliuerance out of Temptation, ſhall be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the foregoing Examples &amp; Inſtances of Gods good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, in ſauing <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Lot,</hi> in the times of their temptation, that is, of their danger &amp; diſtreſſe, wherein the world of the wicked periſhed, as is before in this cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter related by the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>And in this ſenſe alſo you may finde the word <hi>Temptation</hi> often vſed in the holy Scripture. As in the Epiſtle of S. <hi>Iames,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Count it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ioy, my Brethren</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>when yee fall into manifold Temptations;</hi> not of ſinne, but o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> troubles, afflictions and dangers <hi>for well-doing, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe in this ſenſe doth Chriſt himſelfe vſe the word <hi>Temptation,</hi> when he promiſed to the Miniſter of the Church o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:19144:38"/> Philadelphia,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reuel.</hi> 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>deliuerance from the houre of Temptation, that ſhould come vpon the world]</hi> that is, ſaith D. Fulke <hi>[è maximis periculis, &amp; acerbiſſ. calamitatibus,] From the greateſt perils, and moſt bitter cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, that ſhall come, &amp;c.</hi> Now then, the thing is euident, that the LORD our GOD doth here promiſe to all the godly that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon him in the faith of this truth, that he will ſuſtayne, ſaue, helpe, and deliuer them out of their temptations, troubles, and dangers of the greateſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe; and that according to his infinite wiſedome, power, and goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>But it may be here obiected, that this promiſe ſeemeth not to haue beene performed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, vnto the godly, at all times.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19144:39"/>
            <p>I anſwere: Aſſuredly it hath beene, is, and euer ſhall be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, in the full extent, and true ſenſe thereof: I meane, that God wil alwaies either preuent, and repell the euils, and dangers which are imminent, and hang ouer the heads of the faithfull; or elſe will preſerue them vnder the ſame; and finally, either in life temporally, or by death eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally will deliuer them out of al; as here is promiſed. And hereof wee haue a cloud, yea a little world of witneſſes, beſides <hi>Noah</hi> and <hi>Lot.</hi> Let <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Ioſeph, &amp;c.</hi> ſtand forth with their ſtories, and tell vs how the Lord did deliuer them. Yea, let <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons Den; <hi>Ieremie</hi> in the Dungeon, the three Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God in the firie fornace, &amp; <hi>Ionas</hi> in the belly of the Whale
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19144:39"/> deliuer vs in the Records of their preſeruation, for our further co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation. Holy <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſidue of thy Royal race, keepe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot ſilence in this caſe.</p>
            <p>And to come neerer home,<note place="margin">Queene Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.</note> Thou bleſſed Lady of famous memorie, be not wanting to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or this word of Truth, with mine owne ſingular experience: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 88. 92. 94. 97. and in <hi>Anno</hi> 1601. The particulars I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orbeare to mention further, ſith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey are vpon record, and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſly knowne in euery place of his Chriſtian Continent.</p>
            <p>In the laſt courſe (though not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ith the leaſt &amp; worſt euidence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f diuine deliuerance) Let our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſt deare and dread Soueraign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ord King <hi>Iames,</hi> with his royal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pouſe, our noble Prince, Peeres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd whole State come in, and act
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19144:40"/> their parts, &amp; ſhew openly what great deliuerances the Lord of heauen and earth hath wrought out for them, and for vs al inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiuely; wherof we may, we muſt reioyce: and whereof I, in my place, and courſe, according to the truſt that is repoſed in me, &amp; according to the taske that is impoſed vpon me, doe humbly craue libertie of time to make now ſome particular, and perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous Relation of that late (not leaſt) wonderfull Deliuerance of our gracious King, Queene, Prince, State, Church, and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, from that moſt fearefull &amp; helliſh Conſpiracie, now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Treaſon: which is the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall cauſe of our meeting here together in the preſence of God in this houſe of Prayer, this fifth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19144:40"/> of <hi>Nouember;</hi> to the end indeed, that, according to our bounden dutie, wee might ioyntly cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate in this ſacred Solemnitie, the bleſſed Memorie of Gods vnſpeakeable Mercy, gloriouſly ſhewed herein vpon vs all, and vpon our Poſterities, preſent, and to come.</p>
            <p>And becauſe in euery ſet ſpeech ſome order and method would be obſerued, for the better helpe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth of apprehenſion, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, I purpoſe to reduce the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eclaration of this ſtrange ſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ageme, vnto certayne generall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eads, and circumſtances of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reateſt importance. As namely, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſpeake,</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the Conſpirators, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of their qualitie.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the matter it ſelfe, of their Conſpiracie.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:19144:41"/>
            <p>Thirdly, of their pretended colour, or ground of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, of the means which they vſed to performe it.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, of the happy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couerie, and deſtruction both of the Proiect and Perſons ingaged in this horrible Treaſon.</p>
            <p>By this declaration we may be holpen more cleerely to ſee, and ſenſibly to feele the waight and worth of this great Worke of deliuerance, wherewith the Lord that knoweth how to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his out of temptation, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and diſtreſſe, hath bleſſed our King, and Countrie, in his moſt faithfull mercy. The names of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lay-Conſpirators were theſe which follow:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Winter,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Grant,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Fawkes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Percie,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Catesby,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Wright,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19144:41"/>
                  <item>7. <hi>Digby,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. <hi>Rockwood,</hi> &amp;</item>
                  <item>9. <hi>Bates,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10. <hi>Winter Iun.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>11. <hi>Keyes,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>12. <hi>Treſham.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> Men drunken with the dregs of the Romiſh grape, and deepely dyed in the bloud-red-wine of the Whores Cup, inſpired with her curſed ſpirit, and grounded vpon her pernicious Principles. But to leaue theſe awhile; let vs in the ſecond courſe giue in the names of the Clergie-Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. And a wonder it were (I trow) in any miſchieuous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot of either deſtruction, or publike diſturbance of any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian State, therein to finde Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts, and Ieſuites to be meere ſpectators, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maine Actors. I finde of this ſort no leſſe then three ingaged in this one truculent intended Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, viz. <hi>Teſmond, Gerrard,</hi> and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19144:42"/>
               <note place="margin">Perfidioſiſſ. iſte Ieſuita, homo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus exproditione compoſitus.</note> 
               <hi>Garnet,</hi> that moſt perfidious Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite, a man wholly compoſed of trayterous deadly Drugs. To whom the Church and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weale of <hi>England</hi> may iuſtly ſay (giuing him here his breede, and bringing vp) as ſometimes <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneſtra Agamemnons</hi> wife ſaid to her wicked ſon <hi>Orestes,</hi> when he drew out his ſword to runne her thorow:<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>Whether bendeſt thou thy ſword (thou Monſter of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde) againſt the Wombe that did beare thee, or the Paps that gaue thee ſucke?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let vs all with due dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation declayme againſt him, as long ſince One did againſt ſuch another Caytife: <hi>Oh wretched Man, more ſauage then any brute-beaſt! all abhorre thee; for thou wouldeſt haue deſtroyed all.</hi> But let vs leaue their perſons to the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19144:42"/> Lord, who hath ſent them to their appointed place.</p>
            <p>And come we now to their Proiect, euen to the matter it ſelf of their inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Treaſon; which (for order ſake) I will reduce vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three heads.</p>
            <p>Whereof the firſt was,<note place="margin">Primae impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis flagitium.</note> moſt cruelly to haue murthered the ſacred Perſon of our moſt deare and dread Soueraigne, and of his royall Spouſe, Poſteritie-male, together with his Highneſſe Peeres, &amp; State, the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, and Temporall, Knights, Burgeſſes, and whole Body of the Parliament-houſe; all at one bloudie blow, and mercileſſe Maſſacre. Oh horrible Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignement, farre exceeding all proportions of precedent Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie!</p>
            <p>The next head, and ſtrayne of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19144:43"/> this treaſon was,<note place="margin">Parce Ciuium ſanguini.</note> vtterly to haue ruinated the flouriſhing Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of this Chriſtian Kingdome, by rayſing ſeditions and rebellions in euery part thereof and that vnder colour of defending thereby their Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Cauſe, and Perſons. <hi>Apage!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, (which yet with them was not the leaſt) this cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Proiect pitched at this point, euen vtterly to haue ſubuerted the ſtate of true Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion eſtabliſhed amongſt vs by publike authoritie: and in place thereof, to haue ſet vp their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh impieties, with the cruell tyrannie, and curſed Hierarchie of the Romane Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>So that in this horrible inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Deſolation,</hi> there ſhould haue beene <hi>ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Rex, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Lex, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Reſp. in tuto relicta.</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:19144:43"/> Neither King nor Kingdome, Religion nor Lawes left inuio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable. And thus much of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall parts of this prodigious Complot.</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſee what faire co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour the Deuill could caſt vpon this foule Caſe, and with what pretext his Clients could coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance this helliſh Proiect. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily euen this,<note place="margin">Totius iniuſtitiae nulla capitalior peſtis, quàm eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum qui, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>That our bleſſed Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe Chriſtian King, his Queen, State, People, and all (except Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Catholikes) are all damnable Heretikes, and Apoſtataes; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently doe all ſtand</hi> de iure <hi>at leaſt, if not</hi> de facto, <hi>really excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and accurſed: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that it is not onely lawfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nequitiae claſſes candida vela ferunt.</note> 
               <hi>but laudable, yea meritorious, to deſtroy vs all as one Man.</hi> Reade for this purpoſe <hi>Symanca de Excommunic.</hi> and <hi>Creſwels Philopater.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:19144:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Secondly, of their fierie Champions.</p>
            <p>From their Motiues, let vs proceede to ſpeake of their meanes, by which they would haue effected this moſt barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Murther: namely, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring Gun-powder; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they intended to haue blown vp the Parliament-houſe at the then next full and royall Seſſion there. To which purpoſe they had hyred a Vault, or Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, which was vnder the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-houſe, and in the ſame had beſtowed (as it is recorded) ſixe Hogſheads, and twentie Barrels full of Gun-powder, with barres of yron, pieces of timber, and great maſſie ſtones laid therevp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; all which they couered with billets and hoſtrie faggots not a few. All this in a readineſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19144:44"/> the fifth of <hi>Nouember,</hi> 1605. now full eleuen yeeres ſince, this very day of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, &amp; of the Weeke, Tueſday, when all ſhould at the appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted houre haue beene fired by <hi>Guy Fawkes</hi> (that forlorne boute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feux) and his complices: that ſo not only that ancient and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable houſe of Parliament might haue beene vtterly ruinated, but alſo the ſacred perſon (<hi>oh quàm horret animus hoc vel referre!</hi>
               <note place="margin">Peccatum ſine nomine adaequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</note> how doth my heart abhorre to mention it!) of our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious King, Queene, Prince, Peeres, &amp;c. ſhould thereby haue beene blowne vp, and ſplit in pieces, legs, armes, head, heart, bowels, and bones tortured, ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, and carryed vp as high (if it had beene poſſible) as the Moone; to the extreme horror
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19144:45"/> not onely of men and brute beaſts, but alſo of the feathered Fowles, and very Meteors; <hi>&amp; certè quid hic ampliùs dicam, neſcio. Rebus ſic ſtantibus:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs lift vp our amazed mindes to the conſideration of the higheſt mercie in this proie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted miſerie, and ſee how Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and heauenly Prouidence preuailed and triumphed glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ouer Hell and Helliſh Proiects. For euen now ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, when this horrible mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould haue beene acted the next morning, though the verie Quinteſſence of the wit of men and Deuils, ſublimed to the higheſt Sphere, could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly worke more preciſely by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious bond of Oath and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, nor more punctually in reaſon and policie, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenting
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19144:45"/> of diſcouery in this caſe; yet behold, behold, and wonder how no leſſe eaſily, then graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, the Lord our God <hi>(againſt whom no wiſedome, nor counſell can preuaile, and that knowes euerie worke of the Minde)</hi> did defeat and ſcatter their counſels, and wicked imaginations, &amp; broght their enterpriſes to nought; euen eluding them in the very Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke of truſt, by one of their owne complices, which cauſed all the reſt to faile in the point of practice.</p>
            <p>Lend mee your eares a little with ſingular attention, and you ſhall heare me truely relate vnto you, how diuine Prouidence in due time (euen when there was but a ſtep between vs &amp; death,) ſtepped forth, and with a graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hand turned the wheele, yea
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19144:46"/> the ſtreames of deſtruction ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, the right way, by brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to light a few howers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the intended Maſſacre, a darke and doubtful Letter, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by one of the Conſpirators, and ſent (by way of Caution) to the Lord MOVNTEAGLE, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, to forewarne him not to come at the Parliament-houſe on the morrow: for (ſaid that Letter) <hi>A moſt terrible Blow will then and there be giuen to all that ſhall be aſſembled, &amp;c.</hi> This letter being with good expedition ſent to ſome of his Maieſties Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Priuie Councell, was by them eftſoones conueyed to his Highneſſe hand, who peruſing and pondering the ſame, did (no doubt by a diuine inſtinct) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſcouer the Plot; pointed at the very place, and gaue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19144:46"/> that priuie ſearch ſhould there be made: which being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed accordingly, the whole Stratageme was diſcouered, and the parties therein ingaged were brought to light, to Tryall, to Iudgement, and Death.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32.</note> 
               <hi>Oh then loue yee the Lord, all his Saints: for the Lord preſerueth them that are faithfull, and plenteouſly rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the proud-doer. Great plagues remaine for the vngodly; but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer trusteth in the Lord, mercie ſhall imbrace them on euery ſide. Wherefore alſo let our ſoules reioyce in this his great Saluation, and ſing prayſe vnto his holy Name, becauſe hee hath dealt ſo louingly with vs. Bleſſed bee the Lord our God for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and euer. So be it, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to conclude this Diſcourſe to you (right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, and Religious Auditours)
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19144:47"/> in this Grand Cauſe of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned comfort, giue mee leaue, before I leaue this ſacred Cell, to paralell, and ſute ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable Occurrences coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to this ſubiect, ſome with better, ſome with like correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence both of ſpeech and ſpirit.</p>
            <p>I find in reading the publike Records of this Caſe, that <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> that Arch-Traytor, a little before the appointed day of our death (by their Calendar) did cry out, and pray to this effect: <hi>Auferte gentem iſtam perfidam, de finibus credentium:] Take away this perfidious Nation, (meaning vs Engliſh Proteſtants) from the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of true Beleeuers, (intending Romiſh Catholikes:) vt laudes inde Deo debitas alacriter perſoluamus:] that wee (Catholikes) may ioyful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly render due prayſes to God for the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:19144:47"/>
            <p>And againe he praied, ſaying, <hi>Non pacem petimus, Superi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dedit Deus hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> funem.</note> 
               <hi>date Gentibus iras: Wee</hi> (ſaid hee) <hi>pray not for peace, O Heauens, but for puniſhment, to this Engliſh Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs with ſober and ſacred zeale, anſwere his bitter and braine-ſicke bellowings, and crie to our GOD, the GOD of peace, and ſay, <hi>Nulla ſalus bello, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem te petimus omnes: Wee humbly craue of al hands continuance of our peace and ſafetie from thee, O Lord, that canſt eaſily reforme, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the cauſers of our trouble, and diſturbers of our publike peace, and State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to giue correſpondence alſo to a ſecond and better Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence; Let this louing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Citie of <hi>Norwich</hi> cry out, and ſay, as that euer-faithful and famous Citie of <hi>London</hi> did, in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19144:48"/> the day of this their and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance: <hi>Adhuc ſalua eſt Ciuitas noſtra, adhuc ſalua Patria, adhuc ſalua Religio; Rex nempe noſter</hi> IACOBVS <hi>adhuc ſaluus eſt. Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu-iah, Legnolam, Legnolam: Our Citie is yet in ſafetie, our Countrie, Religion and King, bleſſed be God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And finally, let vs all with one accord (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) proclaime with the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in another caſe, and ſay: <hi>This is the day that the Lord hath made</hi> (a day of deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, of ſaluation, and of reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing:) <hi>Let vs therfore bee glad and reioyce therin with holy ioy, all the dayes of our life: yea let vs tell our children, and childrens children what great things the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe hath done for vs, whereof wee may, we muſt reioyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let our Gracious King confeſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.</note> and ſay with holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19144:48"/> (Eodem &amp; animo &amp; nomine.) The Lord liueth, and bleſſed be my ſtrong Helper, and prayſed be the God of my Saluation; euen the God that ſeeth that I bee auenged. For this cauſe wil I giue thankes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord among my People, and ſing vnto his Name: For great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerances giueth hee vnto the King, and will ſtill ſhew mercie vnto his Anointed, euen vnto</hi> IAMES <hi>his Seruant, and to his Seed for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let all the Reuerend and holy Clergie of <hi>England</hi> make vp the Quire, and with the holy Tribe of <hi>Leui, Pſal.</hi> 134. bleſſe both King, Queene, Prince, State, Church, Commonwealth, all in one, and ſay;
<q>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The Lord <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah</hi> that hath formed the Heauens, and the Earth, bleſſe thee out of Sion.</note>Iebarecca Iehouah mittzijon gnoſcheh ſchamaijm vaarets. Amen, Amen, Amen.</p>
                  <p>So be it, euen ſo be it, Amen.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
